Okay,
we're going to start right now. This is hopefully going to be
working. We are on דף כ"ו, daf chaf-vav, עמוד א', amud aleph,
at the משנה. mishna. So back to a few of the topics
we had discussed before with more elaboration. חביתי כהן גדול, chavitiei kohen
gadol, so the חביתין chavitin which we had mentioned was that special
מנחה mincha that the כהן גדול kohen gadol had to bring every
day, half in the morning and half at night, evening I should
say.
לישתן ועריכתן ואפייתן בפנים. lishatan, va'arichatan, ve'afiyatan bifnim. So there are obviously
a number of steps to get to the point where you're going
to have this מנחה, mincha, so let's say you have to get
the wheat, right? You have to grind it, you have to do
all, you have to sift it, you have to then you have
to knead it, then you have to shape it, and you have
to bake it, right? There are all those things you need to
do.
And who was eating? The עד הכהנים ad hakohanim with
him?
I'm trying to remember what happened with that. So וכל מנחת כהן
כליל תהיה לא תאכל, vechol minchat kohen kalil tihyeh lo tachel, right?
So if it was a מנחה mincha of a כהן, kohen, then
it's burnt completely on the מזבח, mizbeach, I thought. So I don't
think anyone eats it unless I'm mistaken.
And he gives half in the morning and half at night, right.
So
the end
parts of this list, of these processes, the kneading, the shaping, and
the baking, that had to be done בפנים, bifnim, inside,
meaning inside the עזרה azara of the בית
המקדש, beis hamikdash, ודוחות את השבת vedochot et hashabbat since it's a
מנחת תמיד. minchat tamid. This is something that always had to be
done every day, twice a day, and needed to be done on
שבת. shabbat. However, טחינתן והרקדתן אינן דוחות את השבת. techinatan veharkadatan einan
dochot et hashabbat.
But the grinding of the flour and the sifting of it all,
because remember you had to put it in a whole bunch of
these sieves, so that did not override or push off the שבת.
shabbat. כלל אמר רבי עקיבא, klal amar rabbi akiva, so he made
a general rule or stated a general rule: כל מלאכה שאפשר לעשותה
מערב שבת אינה דוחה את השבת ושאי אפשר לעשותה מערב שבת דוחה
את השבת. kol melacha she'efshar la'asotah me'erev shabbat einah dochah et hashabbat,
veshe'ee efshar la'asotah me'erev shabbat dochah et hashabbat.
So to sum up, and we have the same principle on יום
טוב yom tov too, that anything you could have done beforehand you
can't do then. Anything you couldn't have done beforehand, then you can
do then. So the same thing with יום טוב, yom tov, we
say you can cook on יום טוב, yom tov, but it doesn't
mean you can go out and cut wheat and then
harvest
it and then grind it, right? Only things that from a certain
point on. So over here it's from לישה lisha ואילך. ve'eilach. So
anything from
לישה, lisha, that דוחה את השבת. dochah et hashabbat. Exactly as to
why let's say you couldn't knead it yesterday, I guess dough really
won't sit too well if you just leave it there in a
vessel, they didn't have refrigeration or anything like that, let's say you
did it before שבת. shabbat. You couldn't anyway do it until the
next day, right? And you had this whole
thing you had to take a whole thing and divide it in
half so you couldn't even put in any of the flour until
the next day anyway. So anyway the point being that these were
things that you couldn't do
beforehand.
But you can definitely
grind, you
can definitely have made the flour before the day before and sift
it and all that before. The next day when he comes in,
then he takes whatever the measure of flour is,
the עשרון, issaron, and then he puts it in the כלי שרת
kli shares and half and half, oil,
no oil or water?
Yeah, no, לישה, lisha, you
have to do the water. But anyway those things are done on
שבת. shabbat. So you can knead the dough on שבת shabbat and
you can bake it on שבת shabbat but you can't do any
of the other things beforehand on שבת. shabbat. So you already had
to have the flour, so that's what we're saying.
Okay now the next line, it's a little bit ambiguous as to
how to take this.
I'll first state it: כל המנחות יש בהן מעשה כלי בפנים ואין
בהן מעשה כלי בחוץ. kol haminchot yesh bahen ma'aseh kli bifnim ve'ein
bahen ma'aseh kli bachutz.
So does this mean every single מנחה mincha or does it mean
that or is it really kind of going on what we just
said before? Or it basically means that all those מנחות minchot that
really need to be done inside need a כלי שרת, kli shares,
right? Because it seems to be a little bit redundant because we
just talked about everything that has to be done בפנים, bifnim, but
here it seems to be here that the חידוש chiddush is either
that it needs a כלי, kli, right? It needs a כלי שרת,
kli shares, that's what we're saying, in the courtyard, or it can
mean that for every single מנחה mincha all these things needed to
be done, לישה, lisha, what we just mentioned, these steps,
that all needed to be done inside the עזרה. azara. Because if
you remember we had come across other משניות mishnayot that seem to
indicate there's a lot you can potentially do at home, right? So
yeah. And at a minimum though, this is saying that if you
say that this is referring to all מנחות, Menachos, then the לישה
Lisha and all that needed to be done from לישה Lisha onward
needed to be done inside the עזרה. Azara. But you could still
potentially let's say you've made your flour at home and then measured
it out at home, sifted it, all that because we said from
קמיצה Kemitza and onward is מצות כהונה. Mitzvos Kehuna. Now we're saying
maybe קמיצה Kemitza is when the כהנים Kohanim get involved, but לישה
Lisha already had to brought it into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
beforehand because the לישה, Lisha, if you're saying this is going on
all מנחות, Menachos, because the לישה, Lisha, the kneading, has to be
done in כלי שרת Kli Shares inside. Doesn't necessarily mean the כהן
Kohen needed to do it, you could've still done it, but
at any rate it needs to be done inside, at least for
the
חביתין. Chavitin. And again the question is does כל מנחות Kol Menachos
really mean כל מנחות Kol Menachos or all מנחות Menachos like
these, לישתן ועריכתן ואפייתן בפנים ודוחה את השבת, Lishtan Va'arichatan Ve'afiyatan Bifnim
Vedocha Es HaShabbat, let's say לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, that kind of
thing,
or the שתי הלחם, Shtei Halechem, maybe it's referring to those two
things. Anyway, whichever way you take it, those need to be done
in
a כלי שרת Kli Shares inside the
עזרה. Azara. שתי הלחם, Shtei Halechem, now today's דף Daf is going
to involve some basic math and visual spatial skills, so I'll try
to make it as easy as possible. Yeah, I'll try to make
it as easy as possible and I actually brought the picture books
which actually does make it a lot easier because we're going to
be referring to them.
So I have it out. We'll refer to it soon enough.
Okay,
so
שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem ארכן שבעה טפחים. Arkan Shva'a Tefachim. We're going
to talk about the dimensions of the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem which
are brought on שבועות. Shavuos.
Seven? So that's like seven like this? That's not so big.
But we're talking about length, so this would be the length.
Yes, so that's like...
so seven טפחים, Tefachim, I don't know, one, two...
like חלה? Challah?
Like a large חלה? Challah? So this big, okay? So it's very...
it's quite big. So it was seven ורחבן ד' Verachban Arba by
four, right?
And then וקרנותיהן Vkarnoseihen now
it has like these horns, you know like think about the מזבח
Mizbeach had four horns, right? So וקרנותיהן ארבע אצבעות. Vkarnoseihen Arba Etzbaos.
It wasn't square, was it square?
No, it was a rectangular, it was seven by four, so it
couldn't have been square.
I meant it had cornered when you say the horn...
It seems like it was.
So it wasn't braided? It was like our...
No, it wasn't braided,
it was not braided.
No, it wouldn't have been braided but it was like not
round.
It was... okay...
it had to have sides to have horns, right?
Well, I don't want to say sides, you know, it had a
thickness but we're talking about the width and now I don't want
to say the height in the four, the height in the corners,
right? Think of the... again, think of the מזבח. Mizbeach.
That's the bread? That's the... that's like the... No?
Here, this one has a... this one has the שתי הלחם. Shtei
Halechem. I can show you.
That's the... that's the table? That's for the... I don't know what
that...
here, this is the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. Oh!
Oh,
weird looking! Okay. Ha! That's
over there. Okay. One picture says this.
It's like European bread. I'm sorry?
European bread, you mean the...
like a brick? Like that? It was four pounds.
So that was the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem.
And just kind of keep that in mind for לחם הפנים Lechem
Hapanim which is similar but got folded.
Okay, so now we got, if you remember, we don't need to
remember this for too long, but seven אצבעות? Etzbaos?
That's what we were...
right, so it was seven by four טפחים Tefachim and then וקרנותיהן
ארבע אצבעות. Vkarnoseihen Arba Etzbaos. So you know,
I
guess you can... four אצבע Etzba either high or maybe it's like
wide?
Or the horns.
Those corners... the corners... okay. We call it וקרנותיהן Vkarnoseihen because it
looks like horns. Alright, לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim which was brought and
put on the שולחן. Shulchan. ארכו י', Arko Yud, so it's a
little bit bigger, right?
ארכו י' טפחים ורחבו ה' טפחים וקרנותיו ז' אצבעות. Arko Yud Tefachim
Verachbo Hey Tefachim Vkarnosav Zayin Etzbaos. So it was bigger. Now, instead
of seven by four by four אצבעות, Etzbaos, this was ten by
five by seven אצבעות. Etzbaos. So it was bigger.
Did you say again what's...
the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem is brought on שבועות Shavuos and לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim was put on the שולחן. Shulchan. Only שבועות? Shavuos?
Only שבועות. Shavuos. And
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim was every... every week on the שולחן. Shulchan.
So that was the bigger one.
That was the bigger one.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says... רבי יהודה אומר שלא תטעה זדד
יהז. Rabbi Yehuda Omer Shelo Titeh Zadad Yahaz. You know, so those
are the numbers. Because right, it was seven by four by four
for the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem and then לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
was יהז, Yahaz, 10 by 5 by 7 אצבעות. Etzbaos. Just in
case you remember, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the one that...
Is he in the הגדה? Haggadah?
Yeah, I think he was. He's the one that liked these mnemonics,
דצך עדש באחב. Detzach Adash Beachav. So he does that again. Jeanette,
you remember רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's the one that—is he in the
הגדה? Haggadah? Yeah, I think he was. He's the one that liked
these mnemonics, דצ"ך עד"ש באח"ב. D'tzach Adash B'achab. So he does that
again here. Obviously, it doesn't tell you which was which, right? You
just remember the seven. If you can remember דצ"ך D'tzach יה"ז, Yahaz,
you need to know which one was for which. He doesn't tell
you how to remember which one was לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim versus
שתי הלחם, Shtei Halechem, but at least you can get that. We'll
test you on it tomorrow. So בן
זומא Ben Zoma אומר, omer, it's kind of what בן זומא Ben
Zoma is going to say is it's a little bit difficult to
figure out what he's really trying to get at, but ונתת על
השולחן לחם פנים לפני תמיד, Venatata al hashulchan lechem panim lefanai tamid,
לחם פנים שיהיו לו פנים. Lechem panim sheyihiyu lo panim. Okay. So
he's saying that, you know, it says you have to put on
the לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, and it really means it has to
have a פנים, panim, like a face. It doesn't really
say
much because other people are going to start talking now as well.
But maybe because of, maybe his is more introductory statement
to the following opinions in the משנה, Mishnah, so let's just see.
So now this is how you do it. Very specific. If you
remember, we had the מחלוקת machloket before whether it was like a
box or like a dancing boat.
So we're not getting into this
exactly
now. This could potentially go either way, because that was more the
shape and these are kind of the dimensions.
Now
the
שולחן—what Shulchan does it mean
שיהיו לו פנים? sheyihiyu lo panim?
Right, that's what I'm saying. He doesn't explain it.
So it means it has to have a face. So, you know,
maybe potentially means different surfaces. Maybe a top? Like it has—right, I
mean he doesn't say, so it's kind of hard to translate and
it doesn't seem
to have a top.
So what I'm saying is I mean the best explanation is what
we're going to see later on in the גמרא Gemara in a
minute.
So let's just see. So now the שולחן, Shulchan, the dimensions are
אמתים ארכו ואמה רחבו. amatayim orko ve'amah rochbo. Okay? So it's two
by one.
That's the שולחן. Shulchan. That's the שולחן. Shulchan.
Well, we'll get to that. There's some really good pictures over here.
Whatever
it was, length, width, right? So it's אורך, orech, which is generally
length, was twice its width, right? Okay, so now there's a—and these
are all in אמות. amot. So now אמה amah can be divided
into smaller units, right? Just like a foot can be divided into
inches. An אמה amah is divided into smaller units, and that would
be טפחים. tefachim.
So the question is how many טפחים tefachim to an אמה, amah,
right? So if you want to get everything in טפחים, tefachim, like
let's say you want to get everything into inches, you need to
figure out how many inches make up an אמה. amah. So how
many טפחים tefachim make up an אמה? amah? So there's a מחלוקת
machloket on this. It's either five or six.
So if you get five טפחים tefachim into an אמה, amah, an
אמה amah is five טפחים, tefachim, and if you get two אמות,
amot, an אמה amah is then ten טפחים, tefachim, right? That's so—if
you get six טפחים tefachim into an אמה, amah, an אמה amah
is six טפחים, tefachim, and two אמות amot would then be twelve
טפחים. tefachim. And that's going to be important coming up in a
few.
I'll just mention it now. All
right, so השולחן ארכו י' ורחבו חמישה. Hashulchan orko yud verochbo chamishah.
This is the first opinion. If you hold that an אמה amah
is five טפחים, tefachim, then if you get two אמות, amot, you
get ten טפחים, tefachim, like I mentioned, ורחבו חמישה, verochbo chamishah, and
if you get one אמה, amah, you get five טפחים. tefachim. Okay.
Now everyone's going to agree to this, that לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim,
like we just mentioned before, ארכו י' ורחבו ה', orko yud verochbo
hey, right? We mentioned that before, that the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
is ten by five, right? So
now—right, right, but but but
you're not putting it the same way. In other words, if you
just put it flat, then the length would correspond to the length
and the width would correspond to the width, but you're not putting
it—you're not putting it the same way. You're putting it the other
way, right? In other words, you're putting the length to the width.
So how do you do that? So basically what you need to
do is if you're putting the length to the width, then you're
getting something that's ten טפחים tefachim in a space of five טפחים,
tefachim, right? You got that? Because the width was five טפחים tefachim
and here the width is five טפחים. tefachim. So you need to—this
is obviously a lot bigger, so it
doesn't—this, right? You need to get something that's, you know, longer in
a space that's shorter, right? It's obviously not to scale. So what
you need to do then, if you need to get something that's
ten to five, you had to fold up the edges, right?
Aha.
So the ten was not the entire base, the ten is the
whole
width, which is actually both sides. Because the שולחן, Shulchan, if you
remember, the שולחן Shulchan had six and six, right?
So that's the length and the width was five. So you're going
to get—so you have to—if you're putting—again, this may—this works better, let's
say you have two of these, right? So we're just talking about,
you know, one column, right? So you got to get the
five—so you got to get a ten in a five, right? And
then you're going to do the same thing on the other side.
No, no, no, so then
the
base—the ten of the base of the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim includes
the folded-up side?
No, no, that's what we're talking about. We
have ten, so you're going to have to get something ten in—
And it has then this maybe is what the פנים panim comes
in so you have to have faces so there's a face on
one side and a face on the other side so you have
to get two sides and you divide five by two you get
two and a half right?
So what are you saying then it's a I would think the
middle is the face.
Well I mean yeah but that's don't concentrate on the face part
but what we're trying to do is fit something that's ten in
a space of five and you gotta whatever you do on one
side you do on the other. So if so you know again
you have five for the middle right? Then you have still five
left so
each side is two and a half so you just fold it
up.
Okay so the other guy says the same thing but since his
measurement is bigger instead of folding up two and a half he's
going to fold up two and we'll get to that in a
second you'll see. So basically נותן ארכו כנגד רחבו של שלחן וכופל
טפחים ומחצה מכאן וטפחים ומחצה מכאן נמצא ארכו מלא רחבו של שלחן
דברי רבי יהודה.
Noten arko keneged rochvo
shel shulchan vechofel tfachim umimtza mikan vetfachim umimtza mikan nimtza arko melo
rochvo shel shulchan divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's
what I just said. So you know the length fills the width
so to speak because you know you basically turned it right like
I said. So you know and you get two and a half
each on each side. Then we're going to get to the corners
in the גמרא. Gemara. We didn't talk about the corners yet. So
and we didn't talk about the thickness of it yet either but
that's going to come up in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay so that's
the first opinion of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says that an
אמה amah is five טפחים. tfachim. Right so here that's this is
our visual spatial skill and mathematics skill. This is going to get
a little bit more in the גמרא. Gemara. So השולחן ארכו רבי
מאיר אומר Hashulchan arko Rabbi Meir omer so
the second opinion is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir שולחן ארכו יב ורחבו
ו shulchan arko yud-bet verochvo vav right? I mean and the לחם
הפנים lechem hapanim still ארכו י ורחבו ה. arko yud rochvo hei.
So they have the same dimensions for לחם הפנים lechem hapanim just
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir שלחן shulchan was a little bigger in terms
of טפחים. tfachim. I mean it has to be the same in
אמה amah but again the question was how big you say an
אמה amah is. So if he says like I mentioned that an
אמה amah is six טפחים tfachim then you get two אמות amot
the
length which is now twelve טפחים tfachim and you get one אמה
amah which is the width which is now six טפחים tfachim because
you know the length was double the width. But he still has
to fit something now something
so then the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim like we just said ארכו
י ורחבו ה. arko yud rochvo hei. So if he is saying
that so now he basically has to get something that's ten in
a space of six right? Two things. No one well what do
you mean? Well whatever you do on one side is the same
as the other. Alright.
So you have to get it's still his his length for the
bread is still י טפחים yud tfachim they both say that. But
now you get the but his width is six his width is
five right?
Which like we said. But now what you need to do is
you need to get something that's ten in space of six. Why
is that? Because again because the width is six טפחים tfachim because
that's an אמה amah and he holds the bread the bread didn't
change those dimensions. Everyone is saying it's ten by five and you
put the length to the width right? So you gotta get something
that's ten in the space of six. The first guy had to
get something ten in the space of five right? Because he holds
an אמה amah is five טפחים. tfachim. He still holds you need
to get this in an אמה amah width and he holds but
he holds an אמה amah that's what changed that's now six טפחים.
tfachim. You get that or is that a little confusing?
Yeah but I don't understand the table what we're doubling everything over.
You're saying the table had two halves. So where do we see
that did they say that in the תורה? Torah? No no no
it says those are dimensions.
Oh right well it says אמתים ארכו ואמה רחבו ואמה וחצי קומתו.
amatayim arko ve'amah rochvo ve'amah vachetzi komato.
But where do we see that it's split in half? That's a
good question. Is it divided like this picture has two with a
line in the middle?
Right well they do say that there's שישה מערכת shisha ma'arechet it
says that. Six on each מערכת. ma'arechet. But and you know but
then how do
you how do you get... Like this table it's not just...
Right no but but if it does say there's שתיים מערכות. shtayim
ma'arachot. שש המערכת. shesh hama'arechet.
It does. Right it does it does say that.
It doesn't say it here but I mean but again like the
table
itself is not divided these are on top of the...
No no no no
this this that
two inch that's a division. It looks like...
That this is a the
table itself is solid.
Right no I know but it is but it isn't.
And the מערכת ma'arechet is the part that's divided.
You mean the sides.
Yeah. Those those look to me like what did the two inches
look like? Two frameworks.
Oh I see or maybe it's the מערכת.
ma'arechet.
Here let me show you.
This this they divide it doesn't look like it's divided.
No it
is because here look see these are two sides.
I understand the space... Well don't concentrate on...
Okay because that depends on who you hold like. So okay but
I'm just trying to what I want you to get out of
this is there are two sides. So we're not concentrating on the
other side
because when we study the size of one loaf we're assuming you're
doing the same thing on the other. Right. Whatever it is you
do on one side you do on the other. What?
Yeah yeah but I don't want you to concentrate I actually didn't
want to do it because
because
then
you're going to have a but then you're going to have a
but I can't visualize...
Then you're going...
No no no I the problem the reason I didn't do that
is because this is according to one opinion.
Like thinking about
it it looks like a lot of food on a
little table.
Yeah this is one table and yesterday רבי Rabbi Linder was talking
about the sides aren't on the table they're next to the table
so it's four and four are next to the table.
Right but again there are so many different opinions of this. This
is according there are so many different opinions of this table. So
anyway so what he has to do since again he holds everyone
holds it's an אמה. amah. Only question is what is an אמה?
amah? Is it a five or six טפחים? tefachim? So if his
אמה amah is six טפחים tefachim right, his לחם lechem is ten
so he has to get something that's ten in a space of
six right? How are you going to do that? The same way
the other guy did it, you fold up the corners. But since
he had to get something that's ten in a space of five,
he got two and a half. So since you get ten in
a space of six you get two on each side right? Because
two then
the middle then the other two. So then we're fine.
Okay. So
that's what he does.
Okay.
טפחיים מכאן וטפחיים מכאן tefachyim mikan ve-tefachyim mikan and then
וטפחיים רווח באמצע כדי שתהא הרוח מנשבת בהן ve-tefachyim revach be'emtza kedei
shetehei haruach menashevet bahen right? Because if you get six טפחים tefachim
you get two then the space is two in the middle and
then another two. That's how you get your six right? So
and then but and this is now that's this picture which I
didn't want to show you until then. So
now again that's how you get you know the quote width. Now
the length
is you get 12 right? So according to the first guy if
you which was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda so if you have five
and five right? Because an אמה amah according to him is five
טפחים tefachim and you have two אמות amot which is the
length right? See each bread is ten by five right? You have
five and five so they're right next to each other right? So
there's no space. So the שולחן shulchan would be basically like this
like the book right? But we hold it's 12 and it's still
five and five right? So then you have two in the middle
right? Because you have five then two then five. That's how you
get your 12. And that would be this picture. So you said
there's a space in the middle. That's according to that's this picture
here. That's according to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. So he has a
space in the middle.
That's what I was getting. There is a space.
Right. But according to רב מאיר Rav Meir it would be right.
So according to
רב מאיר Rav Meir
five a space of two
and then five right?
It's still one solid table.
It's still one solid
table underneath right right because you have to otherwise otherwise it would
just kind of topple over onto the sides or whatever potentially.
So
let me just get my place again. כדי שתהא הרוח מנשבת בהן.
kedei shetehei haruach menashevet bahen. So you know again so you have
a little bit so air can circulate. So that's how you do
that's what was done. So אבא שאול אומר שם היו נותנים שני
בזיכי לבונה של לחם הפנים Abba Shaul omer sham hayu notnim shenei
bezichei levona shel lechem hapanim because remember there's the לבונה levona right?
לבונה levona was the
הרוח מנשבת בהן.
haruach menashevet
bahen. So there was no רווח revach inside
he basically meant like air could circulate so that it won't like
you know if you have the bread all on top of each
other so they'll get moldy. That's what he's saying. So but the
next so what אבא שאול Abba Shaul is saying it's not just
for the רווח revach it's
now point שם היו נותנים שני בזיכי לבונה. sham hayu notnim shenei
bezichei levona. So the לבונה levona was put there in the middle
in that space of two טפחים tefachim you have to put the
לבונה levona which I forget how we translated this. Is it frankincense?
So you know so it was the לבונה levona was offered with
the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. So this that's what these things are
you can see. See this? That's a cup of לבונה. levona. Where?
These spoons. The spoons are לבונה levona whatever you want to call
it. Spoonful you know. So that's what they put over there. That's
the לבונה. levona. That's the handle of the cup for the לבונה.
levona. So they put that there right. Smells nice. And it smells
nice and it was offered on the מזבח. mizbeach. Hopefully smelled nice.
But that's the purpose of the לבונה levona isn't it? To make
the ריח. reiach.
Okay now אמרו לו amru lo so presumably people of the other
camp said והרי כבר נאמר ונתת על המערכה לבונה זכה. ve-harei kevar
ne'emar venatata al hama'aracha levona zacha. So it says you put it
על המערכה. al hama'aracha. המערכה hama'aracha
how would you stack right. So המערכה hama'aracha would be the yeah
the pile. So you put it on the pile not in between
the
pile right.
Also because
there's no room.
We'll get to that. But
what do you mean putting it between? You should put it on
right. אמר להם amar lahem he's a pretty good rhetor. והרי כבר
נאמר ולבנימין אמר ידיד ה' ישכון לבטח עליו ve-harei kevar ne'emar u-le-vinyamin
amar yedid Hashem yishkon lavetach alav right? So when you're talking about
the דגלים degalim you know like we just had the other week's
פרשה parsha you have a you have you know the head of
the whatever like each of the camp right you have the head
of the שבט shevet you also have the head of the דגל.
degel. Says you know and on this דגל degel is this and
on on it is this and on that is this. Does it
mean they're like standing on them? Does it mean that like you
know one שבט shevet is standing on another?
No, rather it means you know near right? So too it doesn't
mean על המערכה al hama'aracha literally means near המערכה. hama'aracha. So basically
you know you could put it in the middle it's near each
מערכה. ma'aracha. So that's a pretty good answer. וארבעה סניפין של זהב
היו שם. ve-arba'ah snifin shel zahav hayu sham. That's what these things
are. These
things. There are four of them right? One, two, then on the
other side another two. So
that's
what we're calling these סניפין. snifin. Two I don't know exactly how
to translate סניפין snifin but you get what I'm talking about. These
yeah good enough.
So there are two panels for each side so four all together
and
מפוצלים מראשיהן mefutzalim
merosheihen
again this is... How you explain מפוצלים mefutzalim is a little bit
contentious. But some people say, this is what Rav Lynch was talking
about. And remember I said sort of like tines of a fork.
Some people say it's like this, believe it or not. The שולחן
shulchan was like this. See this? That's what they mean מפוצלים. mefutzalim.
Some people say it completely. And that's the... סניפים? snifim? No. Well,
yeah, these things were סניפים. snifim. Other people say that מפוצלים מראשיהם
mefutzalim merosheihem means on the sides you had like these little pegs
that protruded. Right? So, you know, think of a coat rack. Or
think, you know, dowels. Okay, dowels. I went to dowels. So, now
what do you need these dowels for? Remember you had those קנים,
kanim, those rods that were put between the לחמים. lechamim. So you
had these little pegs that went out and the rod was hollowed,
so you put the hollowed on the peg. So it stays there.
Right? So that's what those are for. What to take it apart?
So
when you move... No, that was... remember that raises it a little
bit so the air gets through
and supports the bread.
But also when they carried it around when they moved...
No, no, that's something else. That's those are these things. These are...
those are מטות, matot, the staves. Okay. These are the little like,
you know, half hollowed out reeds, rods, whatever you want to call
them,
that they put. So if you had these little dowels that went
out, like these pegs, so you put the rod on, you know,
one end of the rod rested on one end of the peg
on one side. The other end of the rod rested on the
peg on the other side. Because remember you have these סניפים. snifim.
So someone before they were worried about like where the rod would
rest on the לחם?
lechem? We're going to get to that. No, it didn't really matter.
We're going to get to that. We're going to get to that.
Because anyway, just, you know, the end of these
rods rested on the peg. That's one explanation. There are many other
explanations as to what this means. Others say מפוצלים mefutzalim means there
are no pegs necessarily, but you actually made holes in
these סניפים. snifim. And then the rod was even longer then you
put it, you know, so you have like a piece of wood
with a little bit of a hole in it so you can
put the... put it through on one end, you know, put it
through on both sides.
So whatever it is, the rods have something to do with these
פיצולים, pitzulim, however it is you define these פיצולים. pitzulim. Okay. שהיו
סומכים שניים לסדר זה
ושניים לסדר זה. shehayu
somchim shenayim laseder zeh
ushenayim laseder zeh. ועשרים ושמונה קנים כחצי קנה חלול. ve'esrim ushmonah kanim
kechatzi kaneh chalul.
So you have these
24 rods, I mean sorry, 28 rods. And then again, if you
have 28 and you know you have two sides, so 14 on
one side, 14 on the other. Right? Because you know you have
the שולחן shulchan is essentially divided. Right? So,
and it was כחצי קנה חלול, kechatzi kaneh chalul, like a half
of a hollowed out reed. וארבעה עשר לסדר זה וארבעה עשר לסדר
זה. ve'arba'ah asar laseder zeh ve'arba'ah asar laseder zeh. So,
you know, again, if you have 28 in total and you have
two sides of the שולחן, shulchan, so 14 and 14 gets you
your 28. לא סידור קנים ולא נטילתן דוחה את השבת. lo sidur
kanim velo netilatan docheh et hashabbat.
So when
every שבת shabbat you had to, you know, basically put on new
לחם, lechem, so the arrangement of these reeds or taking them off
was not דוחה שבת. docheh shabbat. And we're not really going to
discuss this right now so don't worry about it today. אלא נכנס
מערב שבת ושומטן ונותנן לאורכו של שולחן. ela nichnas me'erev shabbat veshomtan
venotnan le'orko shel shulchan. So, you know, so rather ערב שבת erev
shabbat you took these reeds out
and you put them, you know, aligning the length to the length
of the שולחן. shulchan. And then, again, the גמרא's gemara going to
get into this like, you know, the exact order as to what
was done when.
What was the מלאכה melachah they were doing, building?
I guess it might be מפרק, mefarek, you know, yeah, or then
building, מכה בפטיש. makeh bapatish. I mean we're not sure, but it's
not addressed here now. But whatever it was, it somehow for whatever
reason it's not דוחה שבת. docheh shabbat.
What would you do, why would you touch them once they're in
place? Why?
Because you have to...
you have to get... you have to remove them in order to
get the bread out.
They were holding the bread?
They were holding the bread. Okay. We're the גמרא's gemara going to
talk about that. I mean again, like the גמרא's gemara going to
talk about the whole thing with the... as to what was done
ערב שבת erev shabbat and why, not today. But you'll see, I
mean part of it, it seems that like you really needed to
remove these rods to get the bread out. Like, you know, because
the bread was sort of like indented and made these little indentations
that also rested on the rod. So but we'll get to that.
So don't worry about it just yet.
You have to clean them maybe?
Maybe you have to do that too. Right. I mean I was
thinking that, you know, presumably you had to clean them off so,
you know, maybe some residue got stuck to it, you know, you
didn't want... but at any rate, so this did not דוחה השבת.
docheh hashabbat. So presumably you did it ערב שבת. erev shabbat. You
took these rods out, then you just put all the breads on
top of each other. If you had taken them out ערב שבת
erev shabbat and they had to still be on the שולחן. shulchan.
So but we'll get to that another day. וכל הכלים שהיו במקדש
אורכן לאורכו של בית. vechol hakelim shehayu bamikdash orkan le'orko shel bayit.
This needs to be sort of like just thrown in there. Every...
all the vessels, the utensils of the מקדש, mikdash, the... it corresponds
to the dimensions. Like, you know, the length of the בית bayit
is how you put the length of the כלי, keli, right? So
you know the length of the שולחן shulchan was a length and
width, you put the length to the length. And so too, the
reason potentially this statement is there because it
mentioned the reeds were done
לאורכו של שולחן. le'orko shel shulchan. But we're not going to, that's
not going to be analyzed today. Alright, fine. כל המנחות, kol hamenachos,
this is what we started with, יש בהן מעשה כלי מבפנים. yesh
bahen ma'aseh kelli mibifnim.
Inside it needs to be, it needed to have had certain actions
like we mentioned the לישה lishah the kneading, the עריכה arichah the
shaping, so that had to be done in a כלי שרת kelli
shareis in the עזרה. azarah. בשלמא bishlama to רבי זירא, Rabbi Zira,
מנא הני? mna hani? How do you know? אמר להם, amar lahem,
הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, this is from a פסוק pasuk
in יחזקאל Yechezkel and it always gets a little dicey whenever you
bring anything in
יחזקאל, Yechezkel, but ויאמר אלי זה המקום אשר יבשלו שם הכהנים, Vayomer
elai zeh hamakom asher yevashlu sham hakoanim, need to be the parentheses
but it's inverted, so את האשם ואת החטאת. es ha'asham ve'es hachattas.
So the כהנים, koanim, this is the place the כהנים koanim will
cook the חטאת chattas and אשם, asham, you know, because it's raw
meat, so you know, they're going to they're going to need to
eat it so you have to cook it.
And then also אשר יאפו את המנחה asher yofu es hamencha לבלתי
הוציא אל החצר החיצונה, levilti hotzi el hachatzer hachitzonah, in order not
to take it out, you know, to the outer courtyard. So we
see from here for sure that these things all, and it's מנחה
mincha is in the same breath as
חטאת chattas and אשם, asham, or אשם asham and חטאת, chattas, so
it's all compared. So מנחה דומיא דאשם וחטאת מה אשם וחטאת טעונין
כלי אף מנחה נמי טעונה כלי. mincha dumya de'asham vechattas mah asham
vechattas te'unin kelli af mincha nami te'unah kelli. Just like basically everything
is you needed a כלי kelli for the חטאת chattas and אשם,
asham, you know, either to מקבל דם mekabel dam or to cook
it, so so too from the מנחה mincha you need a כלי
kelli as well and it's all mentioned all this was inside because
you can't take it outside. If you can't take it outside it
had to be inside. So it's all kind of lumped together. I
mean the comparison is a little, it's not exactly one to one,
but you basically see what the thrust of this is, that they're
trying to compare the חטאת chattas and the אשם asham to מנחה
mincha to חטאת chattas and the אשם asham and just like those
things need to be done inside in a כלי, kelli, so too
this needs to be done inside in a כלי. kelli. So that's
how he gets it. השולחן אורכו עשרה. hashulchan orecho asarah.
Okay, so
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, לדברי האומר טפחיים ומחצה כופל, ledivrei
ha'omer tefachayim u'mechtzah kofel, right, and again if you have two and
a half, remember that was getting back to all that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda versus רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, how much you folded in
order, so the first opinion was you folded two and a half,
the second opinion was you folded two. So if you had two
and a half and you have six of them, right, and one
was on top of the other, then basically what you do is
you just multiply six by two and a half and you get
fifteen, right? Trust me on that. So
נמצא השולחן מקדש חמישה עשר טפחים למעלה, nimtzah hashulchan mekadesh chamishah asar
tefachim lemalah, right, so basically, you know, from the, this is on
top, right, you know, you have these fifteen טפחים, tefachim, because you
have again you have six of two and a half, so that's
fifteen.
Well what does that mean the size?
What from from you know from
from the base?
From where you started the bread. Okay, from where you started the
bread you get fifteen טפחים tefachim high. So that's basically what it's
saying if you just...
but there's nothing on the שולחן shulchan that goes high.
Well
those panels, that's at the sides of the bread. So basically you
get, I mean the panel potentially went long, you know, lower down
too to the floor, but we're just talking about from where you
start the bread started.
Okay, and so they're there so that's more
than, but we'll we'll get to that, that's גמרא's gemara question I'm
going to ask about that.
So and this is what we're talking about, how high up does
the airspace go?
We're no, right, we're backing into it. So basically if forget the
airspace for a moment, if you're just piling the breads on top
of each other and you know you just take the two and
a half six times, you get fifteen. That's that's all we're at
right now.
What about the airspace? What? I'm talking about that's the airspace above
the שולחן. shulchan.
Oh, or so you mean, oh I thought you meant airspace between
the breads and then it's not going to be worth fifteen? Oh
okay. Right, yes, yes. Okay. Okay, so לדברי האומר טפחיים כופל נמצא
השולחן מקדש י"ב טפחים, ledivrei ha'omer tefachayim kofel nimtzah hashulchan mekadesh yod-beis
tefachim, right? If you get two, if you you know because that
was the second opinion of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you have two
that you fold on each side and you six breads of two
each high, whatever, so then you get twelve טפחים, tefachim, okay, למעלה.
lemalah. Okay so now והאיכא קנים, ve'hika kanim, right? But then we
have these reeds rods, right? So won't they make it a little
higher? שקועי משקע להו. sheku'ei meshaka lehu. So no, they said it
was these these rods are actually kind of buried in the bread.
So which means they made when they baked it they must have
made indentation on the bottom to get these rods in there, right?
But then it asks wait מאי טעמא mai ta'ama משום דמפיש להו
mishum demapish lehu סוף סוף sof sof קא מפיש להו? ka mapish
lehu? Right? So if your whole point, the reason why you had
these rods was so that the air would be able to circulate
so the bread wouldn't mold wouldn't get moldy. So if you're saying
the bread was the rod was entirely buried in the bread, then
the breads are all on top of each other, then what have
you accomplished? So that's the question. Nothing. So it answers דמגבה ליה
פורתא. demagbah lei purta.
So okay so what they did was, so it wasn't exactly like
buried in the bread, it was like buried a little bit in
the bread, and then the bread rests still on top of it,
they still had a little bit of airspace in between each bread,
right? So basically again what they did is they still made the
indentation so but you know instead of making a big indentation to
cover the entire
rod,
they made a little indentation to cover just like you
know the top part of it.
So were you just talking about the corner where they sat
on top of each other?
No, because they sat, the rod ran
the length of each bread. Now the bread rested on the rods.
So we're saying we have you know if you have the space
of the rods then you have to add that to the space
to the height of the bread. Yeah but what I don't understand
is if this is the shape... Of the bread, right? Yeah, and
each one sat on top of each of the next one,
then why are we worried about
משהו? mashehu? You have it sitting right on top.
Because
you have the space in the middle you're saying.
According to this,
the bread's on top of the bread, essentially.
Yeah, but you also don't know exactly where they,
the shape of
the bread requires there be,
right, no, but no,
right, I hear you, but we also have the, you have the
whole, it's not just, but you also have the whole length, the
whole middle, you know what I mean? Because it wasn't like
they're all on top of each other like this, right? And this
was on top of this, but this also was, you also have
the corners, so it's kind of like this.
There's air in the middle.
The edges there, so it's the whole surface area at the edges
as well.
So I mean if you think of it this way, look at
this picture, just to answer your question, you still have all this
part. Yeah.
So basically, so the question is, okay,
but if we thought that it was,
the rod was not buried in the bread, then you actually have
the height of all the rods, but now we're saying the rod
is mostly buried in the bread, but not entirely. You still have
a little bit of air space between each bread. ואיכא פורתא. Ve'ika
purta.
Okay, fine, so a little bit of air space there, אבל כמאן
דליתא דמי.
Aval k'man d'leita
dami.
I mean it rounds the numbers is basically what they're saying. Okay,
ואיכא בזיכין, Ve'ika bezychim, this בזיכין לבונה, bezychim levona,
right?
So
according to the second opinion, which is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he
put it in between
the stacks. But what about רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right? It wasn't
in between, it was on it, so then you have the height
of the לבונה. levona.
So לגבי דלחם הוי יתבי L'gabbei d'lechem havei yatbei
ולהדי לחם הוי קיימי. Ul'hadei lechem havei kaimei. So
what he holds is, yeah, you put the בזיכין bezychim in like
the hollow of the bread, right? Like you know, you got it?
Here it is, so it's in, they put it on the bread
actually, on the top bread presumably.
Doesn't say which bread, but you know, whatever it was, you can
get it in one of them.
Okay, now we're going to complicate this a bit. ואיכא קרנות. Ve'ika
karnot. So remember we said that קרנות karnot had those horns or
corners, right? The corners were seven אצבעות, etzbaot, remember? That was this
whole little mnemonic over there, which is יה"ז, Yahaz, so the 10
by 5 by 7, seven אצבעות. etzbaot. So now the question is
what is, you know, you have to translate אצבעות etzbaot into טפחים.
tefachim. So
what basically comes out to that is seven אצבעות etzbaot
according to this גמרא Gemara will be one and three-quarters טפחים. tefachim.
Okay, so
you also have the thickness of the bread, right? Because, you know,
the bread wasn't, yeah, it had a thickness, right? So when we
said the 10 by 5 and the seven אצבעות, etzbaot, the one
thing we did not mention was the thickness of the bread. So
now if you're
folding up two and a quarter, two and a half טפח, tefach,
right? But then you also have a טפח tefach thickness. So basically
what you do is,
if you think about it, you have a טפח tefach thick for
each side, right? Because the bread was a טפח tefach thick and
it was folded. So you know, so this part, the thickness is
a טפח. tefach. So you have a טפח tefach thickness, then you
have one and three-quarters טפח tefach for the קרן, keren, then you
have another one and three-quarters טפח tefach for the other קרן, keren,
then you have another טפח tefach for the thickness. So how much
do you get? I'll tell you how much you get. You get
five and a half טפחים, tefachim, right? But what do we say?
We said according to this opinion an אמה amah is five טפחים.
tefachim. So what do you do?
It's too big because you have to fit all that in the
space of five טפחים. tefachim. Do you see that?
Okay, that make sense? So
what he says is, and actually this is a good picture of
this, קרנות לגבי לחם כייף להו ולחם עליהו נייח. Karnot l'gabbei lechem
kaif lehu u'lechem aleihu nayach.
So
you might want to show that picture over there.
I don't know, where was it?
Oh, okay. Yeah, I get it. The
next
page.
See this?
So what they did was they
curved them in, right? The extra, you know, each one I guess
a quarter of a tefach, you have an extra half a tefach,
they had to curve them in
in the middle.
Do you see that? You might want to see this.
So
see, basically our question was you have an extra half a tefach,
what do you do? So they curved them in a quarter of
a tefach on each side so that way they're curved in so
they don't,
so they don't touch each other, right? They may touch each other,
but they're not like, you know,
and that was done through a mold.
Apparently. Well, the mold may just have been on the outside to
get it, you know, this part, this they may have
just... Okay, so, you know, so basic...
okay, so that's
how we
get that.
You'll need a mold
when you bake it.
Well, you put it in the pot. ואיכא מסגרתו. v'ika misgarto.
All
right, now, now he's going to get a little bit...
so
now there's a
מסגרת. misgeret. As you
spray, dough stays in the shape you put it in.
So,
this is a
square though, perfect square.
Okay, I'm just going to read you a few פסוקים. pesukim.
It's not in the גמרא. Gemara. So, ועשית שלחן עצי שטים. v'asita
shulchan atzey shittim. You should make this שלחן shulchan of whatever שטים
shittim is, but of שטים shittim wood, acacia,
acacia, yeah.
We're going to get to that, so it actually makes a difference
what kind of wood it is. אמתים
ארכו, ammotayim orko, length is two אמה, amma, ואמה רחבו, v'amma rochbo,
one אמה, amma, ואמה וחצי קומתו, v'amma v'chetzi komato, and one and
a half height.
That's until the bread. So, וצפית אתו זהב טהור, v'tzipita oto zahav
tahor, you have to cover it in gold, וצפית אתו זהב טהור,
v'tzipita oto zahav tahor, ועשית לו זר זהב סביב, v'asita lo zer
zahav saviv, he made this זר, zer, it's like a crown. Now,
ועשית לו מסגרת טפח סביב, v'asita lo misgeret tophach saviv, a מסגרת
misgeret and טפח. tophach. Question is, what is a טפח? tophach? But
basically, they basically take it to mean that טפח tophach is sort
of like a טפח, tefach, so it's a טפח tefach thick סביב.
saviv. And then ועשית זר זהב למסגרתו סביב, v'asita zer zahav l'misgarto
saviv, you also have to put a crown on this מסגרת. misgeret.
Now, the question is, what is the מסגרת misgeret and where did
it go? So,
before we get on, before we get to this, I'm going to
show you the conclusion, it might be easier to understand. So,
this... there are two opinions of what this מסגרת misgeret is. So,
you had a מסגרת misgeret and you had a דף. daf. Like
so, a דף daf is like, you know, think of like a
flat panel, a solid flat panel. And think of your, think of
your שלחן shulchan right here.
So, you have a שלחן, shulchan, then you have a flat panel,
right? Fine. But it also has the מסגרת. misgeret. So now, the
מסגרת misgeret can either be... if you think of four legs, it
can be the pieces of wood connecting the legs, otherwise those four
legs are just going to topple over. And then, so then you
have a base like this. This would be the מסגרת. misgeret. See
that? All this is the מסגרת. misgeret. Then you put the, then
you put the דף, daf, the panel of the שלחן shulchan on
top of it, right? That is called מסגרתו למטה. misgarto l'mata. The
מסגרת misgeret is beneath, under the דף, daf, right? But others say
no, that you have the legs and then you have the panel,
and let's say, I'm just saying this Gemara, let's say he like
nailed it in, right? And then you had the מסגרת, misgeret, which
is this thing, above the דף, daf, right? Okay? So, two, either
it was part of the...
you connecting the legs, or
it was that thing like a fence.
I'm talking about this, this.
But what about this sort of זר? zer?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's the...
don't worry about that just yet.
So,
because that's also called a מסגרת, misgeret, right?
No, that's a זר. zer.
Oh, זר, zer, that's the crown.
Look at the picture on the right. That's... don't look at the
picture on the left yet.
So, ואיכא מסגרתו, v'ika misgarto, right?
Okay? So,
ואיכא מסגרתו, v'ika misgarto, כמאן דאמר מסגרתו למטה, k'man d'amar misgarto l'mata,
right? So okay, fine. So now, basically, if you're saying that...
because again, we're trying to say like, oh wait, isn't it, isn't
it higher than you're saying it is? Well, if all that was
before the bread started, you have no problem, right? That's the מסגרתו
למטה, misgarto l'mata, because the bread was placed on top of that.
But ולמאן
דאמר מסגרתו למעלה היכי הוה, u'l'man d'amar misgarto l'ma'ala haichi hava, so
what do you do about that, right? If you hold that it's
above and we have a מסגרת misgeret that's a טפח, tefach, and
then you put all the bread above that, then it's a... then
you have an extra טפח tefach that you have to worry about.
And you can't say it's rounding error because they don't round for
a טפח. tefach. So, דפרוקטי הוה מפרכתא וליחמא גבי דשלחן הוה יתיב,
d'peruktei hava mefarkta v'lichma gabei deshiteh hava yasiv, right? So basically, פרוקטי,
peruktei, it was slanted, so it wasn't a full טפח. tefach. So
then, basically, I guess maybe the bottom bread you slanted it also
so that it fit in the groove, so to speak, of the
bread. So does that make sense? So it was slanted and then
you just, you know, angled the, that bottom bread was a little
bit angled, so therefore it wasn't any higher. It was the same
because of that, because it wasn't, you know, a full טפח tefach
flat, it was
sloped.
Does that make sense? It was a sloped. This is what this
is. If you hold it, if you hold the מסגרת misgeret is
above, you have to say it was angled, because otherwise, you know,
the bread would just be an extra טפח tefach high. But if
you angled it, then you basically angle the bottom of the first
bread and, you know, put it there so that it rests on
the, on the
angle.
That's what they're basically saying.
I don't know if there's a picture here for that, but...
Let's make a nice little model for people to put together and
it's like a 3D puzzle. It gives a point to different views.
דתניא רבי יוסי אומר לא היו שם סניפין אלא מסגרתו של שלחן
מעמדת את הלחם.
d'tanya
Rabbi Yosei
omer lo hayu sham sniphin ela misgarto shel shulchan ma'amedet et halechem.
According to Rabbi Yosei, he holds he actually didn't have the, these,
those, you know, side panels, these things. He holds he didn't actually
have that, but rather...
The מסגרת של שלחן מעמדת את הלחם, misgeret shel shulchan ma'amedet et
halechem, the מסגרת misgeret held the לחם. lechem. Obviously what he asks
me is he meant yes, what he asks him is it held
the first one in place
that the and the rest were just,
I'm sorry, and the rest were just, you know, on top of
each other. Right. And the rest, you know, you have these rods
and, you know, which is why we were worried about the גמרא
Gemara a couple pages before like, you know, if you had that
they were like like a ספינה, sfina, how do they stay on
something? You know, they said oh well, you know, they made a
little lip whatever it is to like put it on.
Anyway, so he holds there was no מסגרת misgeret and rather you
had the, I mean there was no סניף, snif, there was no
side panels, everyone holds you have to have a מסגרת, misgeret, you
have to have a מסגרת. misgeret.
And, you know, the bottom that that was sloped on the side,
the מסגרת, misgeret, so you put the first bread at least and
it's, you know, stable. All the one replaced on top of them.
אמר ליה מסגרתו למטה הייתה. Amar leih misgarto lemata hayta. So they
said no, it had a מסגרת misgeret but the מסגרת misgeret was
beneath and, you know, and therefore you had the whole side panels
which were needed to support the לחם. lechem. אמר רבי יוחנן דברי
אומר מסגרתו למטה הייתה טבלה המתפחת טמאה ודברי אומר מסגרתו למעלה הייתה
טבלה המתפחת תיבעי לך. Amar Rabbi Yochanan divrei omer misgarto lemata hayta
tavla hamitpachat tmeia vedivrei omer misgarto lemala hayta tavla hamitpachat tiba’ei lach.
So basically what he's trying to say is this is not directly
related to לחם פנים, lechem panim, but can שולחן shulchan be מקבל
טומאה? mekabel tumah? So that's that's the question. And specifically not just
the שולחן shulchan
but
the מסגרת. misgeret. So if you, I'm sorry, I should say the,
not the מסגרת, misgeret, but the that panel, the דף daf of
the שולחן, shulchan, right, the
tabletop like, you know, this tabletop. So if you hold that the
מסגרת misgeret was below, right, then you just put the top on
on top, right? And there's really no difference which way you put
it, right? It can be this way or that way. But if
you hold that the
מסגרת misgeret
was on top,
you don't really know because this really isn't a
reversible top because, you know, it kind of stayed that way. You
know what I mean? Because, you know, it was the מסגרת misgeret
was on top, so you're not going to have a reason to
reverse it. So
by this whole question, the premise is כאילו שולחן בר קיבול טומאה
הוא, ke’ilu shulchan bar kibbul tumah hu, right? If you're saying can
the, you know, according to the one that says the מסגרת misgeret
was above or below, you know, what about this דף, daf, can
it be מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? Obviously
if they're even asking that it has to be susceptible to טומאה.
tumah. Because if it couldn't be, then you have no question.
So the question is כלי עץ העשוי לנחת הוא וכל כלי עץ
העשוי לנחת אין מקבל טומאה. kli etz ha'asui lenachat hu vechol kli
etz ha'asui lenachat ein mekabel tumah. But wait, why shouldn't it be
מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? You know, we think our premise is that
that a כלי kli has to be a כלי, kli, right? In
other words something you kind of transport with you. These כלים kelim
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash they weren't really meant to be
moved around, except when you, you know, בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash certainly
not, in the משכן Mishkan you could say when they move from
one place to another, but even even then that's more the exception
than the rule. You know, it was meant to just stay there,
especially in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right?
And why do we think it's not מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? Because
מאי טעמא דומיא דשק, mai ta'ama dumiya desak, because there's
a פסוק pasuk
that mentions everything and we've had this question before. Yes, we did.
Yes. We know, you're right. We had exactly that before.
The שולחן shulchan wasn't a movable object.
The פסוק pasuk
says,
they quote it in here, מכל כלי עץ או בגד או עור
או שק, mikol kli etz o beged o or o sak, right?
So wood, which is a שולחן, shulchan, בגד beged or עור or
or שק, sak, right? שק sak is a, how would we translate
that? Like a sack basically. So מדומיא דשק מה שק מיטלטל מלא
וריקן אף כל מיטלטל מלא וריקן, medumesak ma sak mittaltel malei vereikan
af kol mittaltel malei vereikan,
right? Just like a sack, you know, take it full, take it
empty, so too anything else, right? Take it full, take it empty,
but the שולחן shulchan is just going to stay in its place.
No, the answer is שולחן נמי מיטלטל מלא וריקן. shulchan nami mittaltel
malei vereikan. כדריש לקיש. kid'Reish Lakish. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish,
so basically the answer is no, you took the שולחן shulchan too.
When? ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says מאי דכתיב על השולחן הטהור? mai
dicheitiv al hashulchan hatahor? Mentions in the פסוק pasuk on the שולחן
shulchan that's טהור, tahor, right? Well he could he could say that
טהור tahor meant it's made from pure gold or you can or
you can say that it means that the שולחן shulchan needs to
be kept טהור. tahor. טהור מכלל דאיכא טמא. tahor miklal de’ika tamei.
So what, does it mean that if it's טהור tahor that means
it could have been
טמא? tamei? אלא מלמד שמגביהין אותו לעולי רגלים ומראין בו לחם ואומרין
להם ראו חיבתכם לפני המקום. ella melamed shemagbihin oto le'olei regalim umarin
bo lechem ve'omrin lahem reu chibatchem lifnei HaMakom. So it means that
on the רגלים regalim they actually took the שולחן shulchan with the
bread outside, showed it to everybody. So that means how'd they take
it
to
the
pilgrims that were that were gathered there to yeah to show it
to them. Outside. They carried it outside the היכל, heichal, showed it
to the masses that were assembled there and they
said דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי נס גדול נעשה בלחם הפנים. de'amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi nes gadol na’asah belechem hapanim. I skipped. ראו
חיבתכם לפני המקום, reu chibatchem lifnei HaMakom, right? Look how beloved you
are from the in front of God. So before I get to
how beloved you are in front of God, but basically what this
says is that no, it wasn't meant to be or only stationary,
they actually took it at least three times a year to show
it to everybody, so it was moved. So if it's moved, then
it's like a כלי kli and therefore it can be מקבל טומאה.
mekabel tumah.
So now what, how now about this belovedness in front of God?
Oh, what'd he say? What? Translated to showbread sometimes, לחם פנים.
lechem panim. Right. Exactly.
But
they usually spell it with an 'e'. Yeah. They always spell it
S-H-E-W. Oh, yeah. So I don't know why.
I think that was English. But I think it's about showing.
So yeah, at least according to that, it was shown. Rucky, expound
on that. כי דרבי יהושע בן לוי דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
נס
גדול נעשה בלחם הפנים, Ki deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi nes gadol na'asa belechem hapanim, a great miracle happened to
the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, that, you know, just as it was
taken off like it was put on. What does that mean? שנאמר
לשום לחם חם ביום הלקחו, Shenemar lasum lechem cham beyom hikalcho, to
put on warm bread, pop bread, warm hot hot.
That had to people know it was hot, steaming.
Right, exactly.
So that's what they did. So basically, I mean, I don't know
how they're all going to see it at the top, but you
know, they took it out and they were like, look, this bread,
although it was a week later, right? Because it was put on
שבת Shabbat and then a week later is when they ate it.
So you have a whole week where the bread could have become
stale, cold, moldy, whatever, right? So you know, you take it out
and you see the steaming hot bread, you know, maybe the steam
is coming out, whatever it is. And they say, oh look, God
loves you so much that he's doing this great miracle with the
bread is still nice and fresh just like the day it was
put on, looks like freshly made.
This is on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Yeah. So it wasn't a
week?
What? No, but they had to put on the new bread every
week. For שבוס. Shabbos.
So maybe יום טוב Yom Tov was on a Thursday.
That's true. You're right, I guess.
But if יום טוב Yom Tov was on a Thursday and on
a Sunday, then it's like the next day or something.
No, but they
did it three times a year.
It still is a miracle. You bake something on שבת Shabbos and
then not
the next day, but after six days, or eight days potentially. So
maybe
they took it out every one of those...
maybe they took it out every one of those days, but even
then still fresh. Even the next day something remains hot. You know,
bread can stay pretty hot.
Okay, but anyway, you get the point of what they're trying to
do.
If you want, we can go finish to the two dots on
the next page or we can end here, whatever's up to you.
This'll go pretty quickly.
Want to go? I'll keep it easy for Dov. All right. So
now...
you're not going to be here?
Well, one of these days I may take my kids to the
bus, so therefore Dov is going to give it to Ma. So
ותיפוק ליה משום ציפוי, vetipok lei mishum tzipui, this'll go pretty quickly,
ותיפוק ליה משום ציפוי. vetipok lei mishum tzipui. So now
we're trying to figure out again, can it become טמא, tamei, right?
So we're saying, oh, our first question was
it shouldn't become טמא tamei because it's not moved, right? We said,
no, it was moved, so therefore because of that it can be
טמא. tamei. But wait, ותיפוק ליה משום ציפוי. vetipok lei mishum tzipui.
So why can't we answer the question
that the שולחן shulchan was gold-plated, right? And if you assume that
the
plating is what defines the characteristics of the שולחן, shulchan, that, you
know, basically if you're looking at it as wood, what is less...
well,
we'll look into it. So basically, מי לא תנן השולחן והדופלקי שנפחתו
או שחיפן בשיש ושייר בהם מקום הנחת כוסות טמאין רבי יהודה אומר
מקום הנחת חתיכות. Mi lo tnan hashulchan vehadofleki shenifchetu o shechipan beshayish
veshayer bahem mekom hanachat kosot tamein Rabbi Yehuda omer mekom hanachat chatichot.
Okay,
so basically let's say you have this wood and then you plate
it with something, whatever it
is. You plate it with metal or stone... that was this case.
So
a table or a דופלקי dofleki is a chair.
And you know, either you hacked some of it off or you
covered it with
marble, something, right? But ושייר בהם מקום הנחת כוסות, veshayer bahem mekom
hanachat kosot, you left a little bit part that was unplated. There's
a part that was still the way it was before.
So therefore he says טמאין, tamein, they can still become טמא. tamei.
That was the first opinion.
So basically what we're saying is that it's still basically considered
usable, right? And
it retains its identity as an original... basically let's look at the
part that's more important for us is the plating part. You cover
it with marble, right? But you left a part of wood big
enough to put some stuff on, on the wood part, right? So
basically it still retains its identity as wood, right? And
Rabbi Yehuda says you need, it's not enough to put on goblets,
you need to put on some other stuff like pieces of meat,
which is a little bigger than a goblet, let's say. Okay, anyway,
the point is שייר אין לא שייר לא, shayer in lo shayer
lo, right?
So it still retains its identity as wood if you left a
little bit of wood that was not plated. But the שולחן shulchan
was completely plated. It was completely covered with gold, right? So then
according to that, you take on the identity of the gold. Gold
is a metal, metal can be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So then
that should be your answer. וכי תימא קמא דציפוי עמיד קמא דציפוי
שאינו עמיד, Vechitei ma kama ditzipui ameed kama ditzipui she'eino ameed, maybe
you can say it depends whether
the covering is attached. Like, you can say gold-plated but maybe somehow...
I don't know why you'd think this, but potentially you may say
that the covering of the gold plate isn't actually... it wasn't like
dipped in gold, kind of think of a chocolate-covered strawberry. Maybe they
actually kind of put the gold like right next to it, they
abutted it. But it wasn't actually part of it, right? Maybe you
could say that.
Whether or not that actually was the case, but maybe you'd say
that, וכי תימא קמא דציפוי עמיד קמא דציפוי שאינו עמיד, vechitei ma
kama ditzipui ameed kama ditzipui she'eino ameed, maybe it makes a difference
if the covering is attached to the part of the, you know,
whatever it is you're covering. בעי מיניה ריש לקיש מרבי. Ba'ei minei
Reish Lakish me'Rabbi. Rabbi Yochanan בציפוי עומד ובציפוי שאינו עומד. bitzipui omeid
u'vitzipui she'eino omeid. They asked him a question, you know, does does
whatever it is you're covering come subordinate to the plate to the
covering? בציפוי עומד ובציפוי שאינו עומד bitzipui omeid u'vitzipui she'eino omeid בשיפה
את הלביזבין ושלא חיפה את הלביזבין. b'chifa et ha'livzivin v'shelo chifa et
ha'livzivin. So does it make a difference if you plate the rims?
Don't worry about that, but the point is אמר לו לא שנא
ציפוי עומד ולא שנא ציפוי שאינו עומד לא שנא חיפה את הלביזבין
ולא שנא לא חיפה את הלביזבין. amar lo lo shana tzipui omeid
v'lo shana tzipui she'eino omeid lo shana chifa et ha'livzivin v'lo shana
lo chifa et ha'livzivin. Basically any, no matter what, it doesn't make
a difference, you know? It doesn't make a difference if attached or
not attached, but basically if it's plated, it's plated and takes the
identity of the plating, right? So based on that, we have an
answer to our question. Again, the plating was gold, gold is a
metal, metals מקבל טומאה, m'kabel tumah, so then you should know if
it's מקבל טומאה m'kabel tumah or not. So the answer is וכי
תימא, v'chi teima, oh well maybe not so fast, וכי תימא אכתי
חשיבי ולא בטלי. v'chi teima achtei chashivi v'lo batli. Maybe, okay, well
it depends what you're plating. If you're plating something that's not so,
you know, important, then you could say that the plating is the
more important thing. But if you're saying you're plating something that's very
important, let's say the wood is a very valuable wood, they may
still say it retains its identity as wood, right? וכי תימא אכתי
חשיבי ולא בטלי הניחא לריש לקיש דאמר לא שנו אלא בכלי אלכסנדריא
הבאים ממדינת הים אבל כלי ממקומנו חשיבי ולא בטלי, v'chi teima achtei
chashivi v'lo batli hanicha l'Reish Lakish d'amar lo shanu ela bichlei Alexandriya
ha'ba'im mi'medinat ha'yam aval klei mim'kumenu chashivi v'lo batli, right, שפיר דמי.
shafir dami. So it depends, you know? So one opinion was that
yeah, you're right that if you're plating something that's very expensive, then
it retains the identity of wood, in which case then you could
say alright they may have a question as to whether this דף
של שולחן daf shel shulchan could be מקבל טומאה m'kabel tumah or
not because even though it's plated but it's wood and the wood
is important, so maybe the plating, you know, isn't what's so important.
But according to the other opinion, אלא לרבי יוחנן דאמר כלי ממקומנו
נמי בטלי איכא למימר. ela l'Rabbi Yochanan d'amar kli mim'kumenu nami batli
ika l'meimar. Right, but according to Rabbi Yochanan who says that no
matter what you're plating, even if it's something very valuable, it still
retains the identity of the plate, right? So the plating is more
important than then okay well then you should have an answer to
your question. So the answer is שאני שולחן דרחמנא קרייה עץ. shani
shulchan d'rachmana karyei eitz. No, שולחן shulchan is different because even though
normally in everything else the plating is what's more important, but the
Torah calls it a שולחן עץ, shulchan eitz, a שולחן shulchan of
wood, שנאמר המזבח עץ שלש אמות גבוה וארכו שתים אמות ומקצעותיו לו
וארכו וקירותיו עץ וידבר אלי זה השלחן אשר לפני ה'. shenemar ha'mizbe'ach
eitz shalosh amot gavo'ah v'arko shtayim amot u'miktze'otav lo v'arko v'kirotav eitz
va'yedaber elai zeh ha'shulchan asher lifnei Hashem. So it starts out saying
the מזבח mizbe'ach is עץ. eitz. You think he's talking about the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, but then the ending is actually talking about a שולחן.
shulchan. So I'll translate that. It says the altar, מזבח, mizbe'ach, was
of wood, so it was three אמות amot high and two אמות
amot wide, and its corners and the length of its walls were
all of wood. And then Hashem said, this is the table before
Hashem. So we're all talking about the table. And so basically even
though it was plated, it's still called a מזבח עץ, mizbe'ach eitz,
right? It's wood. So, you know, so then we see that it's
a little bit... the שולחן shulchan is a little bit different. Even
though it's plated, the wood is important, in which case then you
ask the question whether, you know, a reversible דף daf can be
מקבל טומאה m'kabel tumah or not. Alright fine. But now one little
final thing of אגדתא Agadata and we'll end with this. פתח במזבח
וסיים בשולחן. patach b'mizbe'ach v'siyem b'shulchan. If you're noticing it says the
מזבח mizbe'ach is wood, etcetera, etcetera, and then the end
of it is זה השולחן אשר לפני ה', zeh ha'shulchan asher lifnei
Hashem, this is the table that's in front of Hashem. So it
starts with מזבח, mizbe'ach, ends with table.
So רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר דאמרי תרווייהו כל זמן שבית המקדש קיים
מזבח מכפר על האדם ועכשיו שאין בית המקדש קיים שולחנו של אדם
מכפר עליו. Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar d'amri tarvayhu kol zman she'Beit Ha'Mikdash
kayam mizbe'ach m'chaper al ha'adam v'achshav she'ein Beit Ha'Mikdash kayam shulchano shel
adam m'chaper alav. So now it's your table. Why? Because you know,
you say ברכת המזון, Birkat HaMazon, you say דברי תורה. Divrei Torah.
Table is like a מזבח, mizbe'ach, that's what we say.
Yeah, that's where we get it from. This is the source. Okay,
יישר כוח. yasher koach.